"Are Plant Sterols Effective for Lowering Cholesterol?"
The Dietary Guidelines cite
the National Academies
in recommending that
"dietary cholesterol consumption
be as low as possible."
While eggs are
the most concentrated source
of cholesterol gram-for-gram,
the greatest contribution
in the American diet is meat,
including poultry and fish.
But even if
our cholesterol intake is zero,
if you remember
from my earlier video,
our liver dumps
excess cholesterol
into our digestive tract
through the bile,
expecting there to be
about a hundred grams of fiber
in there every day
to trap it and flush it
out of the body,
but when people are getting
five to ten times less fiber
than nature intended,
much of that cholesterol
gets reabsorbed
and can circulate
back through our system.
That's why
one of the components
of the cholesterol-lowering
Portfolio Diet
are foods like oatmeal
that are high in sticky fiber
that traps cholesterol,
but the diet also includes
phytosterols, plant sterols.
This is what cholesterol
looks like.
This is what one
of the phytosterols looks like.
It's almost identical.
And the receptor here
in the lining of our intestine
can't tell the difference;
so, the phytosterols
compete with cholesterol
to squeeze in
through this receptor.
So, if there's a lot
of phytosterols in the gut,
some of the cholesterol
can't get in or back in
and ends up in the toilet
instead of our bloodstream.
Here's fecal cholesterol
excretion in people
eating different amounts
of phytosterols.
The black is the amount
of dietary cholesterol
that's being pooped out,
and the white is the amount
of cholesterol
that our liver dumps
into our intestine
through the bile.
With more and more
phytosterol consumption,
more and more cholesterol is
being flushed out of the body.
Now, even if you eat
a strictly plant-based diet
without any dietary cholesterol,
you'd still be getting rid
of more cholesterol
by eating more phytosterols.
Unfortunately,
like fiber intake,
plant sterol intake
is way down in modern diets.
We probably evolved
getting about a thousand
milligrams a day.
But these days
we may only be getting
about 300 milligrams a day,
though those eating
more plant foods
may be getting twice that.
Little bits are found
throughout the plant kingdom
in vegetables, grains,
legumes, and fruits,
but the highest
whole food sources
tend to be nuts and seeds.
Phytosterols may help explain
the cholesterol-lowering effects
of nuts.
But nuts are already a part
of the Portfolio Diet;
why add phytosterols too?
Well, if you look
at the X-axis,
people may only be getting
a few hundred milligrams a day
from nuts.
It turns out
there's a continuous
dose-response relationship
between phytosterol intake
and LDL cholesterol lowering.
Yeah, going from
very few plant foods
to lots of plant foods
can draw more cholesterol
out of the body,
but two grams a day
can draw out even more,
and that translates
into lower LDL cholesterol
in the blood.
So, a really healthy
diet's worth
may drop our LDL
by about six percent,
but two or three grams a day
can drop our LDL
more like ten percent,
and that alone could reduce
our risk of heart disease
by about ten percent
over a decade
or 20% over a lifetime.
That's why we see
heart health guidelines
recommending
the use of phytosterols
as a supplementary strategy
alongside
lifestyle modifications
to decrease
blood cholesterol levels.
Okay, so phytosterols
are effective,
but are they safe?
I'll address that next.